Sometimes bugs in our code are being unnoticed for a while.
And we only notice them when code is already committed.
That would be nice to cancel the last commit or even several last commits and make some fixes. For that "git reset" command is usually used.
We give it the commit to which we want to revert. We can use an identifier, but most of the time we want to get one
or several commits back. As you remember we have to use tilde "~" to get a parent,
and "HEAD" can be referred to with an "@" sign. So "@~" - is a parent of the current commit.
The "reset" command has several flags with which you can call it. Lets have a look at "hard" at first as it is the easiest, so-called hard reset.
Once ran it moves the current branch to the commit provided. Lets change "@~""
to this identifier, actual parent of the "HEAD".
Updates the working directory together with index so that they correspond to the state of the project at the moment of commit.
Running! Done! We rolled back to the previous commit.
"master" now points here and you, probably, could notice the "index.html" got updated in the editor. Now working directory
has a previous version. And if I type "git status" we see the clean status, which means that the working directory
and index correspond to each other and the current and therefore older state of the repository. Like if we didnt make the last commit at all.
Now if I want to continue the development and add some changes and
commit.
Note, the parent of the new commit will be the "HEAD" or the current tip of the "master".
As you see its shown at the right.
Now new HEAD is our last commit. And the further development in the master will be on top of it. And our old commit is not used any more.
In our case its not a part of any branch. It is unreachable
from any branch and therefore will be develed from the database after some time, so we'll have something like this.
So we can use "git reset" to completely cancel the last commit and now I made another commit in its place.
From the other side, life can bring us surprises. Its possible, that we made a reset and then recalled something and we want to get our old commit back.
Furtunately enough git doesnt delete commits right away, so we can get our commit back.
For that Im going to run "git reset" once again and give it that commit that master had previously, this one.
Of course, in real life you dont know the id of this commit or have forgotten it already.
"git log" will not show it as its unreacheable. And we dont have our image with the repository structure in a real life.
Instead we have a "git reflog" command. "git reflog master" - contains all the previous values of "master". Therefore we can find this commit.
Or theres one more option. When "git reset" is moving the branch
it writes the previous value of the "HEAD" into the ".git" directory in the "ORIG_HEAD" file.
And we can use it as a reference. So "git reset" and "ORIG_HEAD". will turn everything as it was.
Dont! "master" is now pointing to the same place as it used to. In the working directory index now is same as it used to be before the last reset.
The only difference is that git database has another unreacheable commit. The one that we've just made.
Its being pointed by "ORIG_HEAD" as we've just left it.
I want to note that "ORIG_HEAD" - its such a second grade link. From one side we can use it in the commands, from the other side
git saves it just in case.
It doesnt use it inside itself. So it doesnt influence on if commit is reacheable or garbage collection. So its just for the convenience it gives.
Later we'll have a look at the other links of this kind, something underscore "HEAD"
that are used by the other git commands. All these links have no influence on the garbage collection.
The orphaned commit will be removed from the database after a while and the structure will become same as it used to be.
So, we've just got one commit back and reverted to initial state.
By default the data,
about the unreacheable commits is stored in the reflog, and therefore in the database for at least 30 days. During this time you can jump back and forth.
Anywhere, so that "git reset" command can be reverted with one exception.
If files changes were not committed, then they will be removed after the "git reset".
Files will just be substituted with the ones which were in the repository at commit time.
If you want to save your uncommitted changes,
we'll learn the "git reset" with the "keep" flag or we can use "git stash". But if our goal is to roll the last change back
then, probably this behavior is more of a pro, than a con.
This pecularity of "reset" command is sometimes used to clear the local directory index of uncommitted changes.
For example, I did something with the files,
experimented, maybe even added some changes to the index, but I dont like them and I want to revert everything as it was.
Running "git reset --hard". If commit is not set, it assumes the current commit which is "HEAD".
By thing branch will not be moved anywhere, but the files and the index will be restored from the repository.
Dont! Status is clean again. Uncommitted changes were removed from both the inedx and the working directory. They're gone.
So, what did we see in this video
hard "reset" is mostly used to completely change the last commits and to remove the uncommitted changes.